<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Essays | Matthew Waddington</title>
    <link>/essay/</link>
      <atom:link href="/essay/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Essays</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Essays</title>
      <link>/essay/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can the way that psychological therapy is delivered by the therapist enhance the benefits for the patient?</title>
      <link>/essay/therapeutic-alliance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/essay/therapeutic-alliance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite much of the empirical evidence highlighting the improvements in patients’ outcome from particular psychological therapies (e.g., Hofmann, Asnaani, Vonk, Sawyer &amp;amp; Fang, 2012), there are also significant benefits from non-specific psychotherapy factors which are used across psychotherapies (e.g., Webb, DeRubeis &amp;amp; Barber, 2010). These factors include therapist adherence, the therapeutic alliance, and therapist competence, to name a few (Tschuschke et al., 2015). This essay will focus on the importance of the therapeutic alliance (TA) in benefitting the patient by means of reducing symptoms and distress. The TA involves a collaboration built between therapist and patient (Buchholz &amp;amp; Abramowitz, 2020). The tripartite model of TA dissects this collaboration into a mutually supportive bond, an agreement on treatment goals, and an agreement on the tasks incorporated to reach those goals (Bordin, 1979). In order to justify and argue that the TA is an important component in the delivery of successful psychotherapy, the following argument will be outlined. Firstly, the robust and consistent finding that the TA is associated with psychotherapy outcome will be discussed. Secondly, a potential causal link between TA and patient outcome will be suggested with research that controls for the time at which TA and outcomes are measured. This will additionally shed light on the benefits of forming an early TA in psychotherapy. Thirdly, it will be suggested that the TA itself not only predicts positive psychotherapy outcomes, but additionally moderates the effect of other non-specific therapy factors. Finally, the therapist’s responsiveness to ruptures that arise within the TA may be one mechanism within the delivery of therapy that enhances treatment success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-importance-of-the-therapeutic-alliance&#34;&gt;The importance of the therapeutic alliance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patients’ outcomes within psychotherapy have consistently been shown to be moderately related to the TA (Fluckiger, Del Re, Wampold &amp;amp; Horvath, 2018; Horvath, Del Re, Fluckiger &amp;amp; Symonds, 2011; Martin, Garske &amp;amp; Davis, 2000). In a recent meta-analysis based on 295 independent samples which included 100 randomised controlled trials (RCT), Fluckiger et al. (2018) revealed an overall mean weighted effect size between alliance and patient outcome of r = .28. Thus, on average, the greater the TA, the greater the patient outcome. Whilst this effect size is only moderate and accounts for 8% of the total variance, it is greater than that of other non-specific therapist factors, such as therapist competence (i.e., the therapist’s expertise) and therapist adherence (i.e., the extent to which therapists’ adhere to a protocol), with an effect size of .07 and .02, respectively (Webb et al., 2010). Despite this meta-analysis finding high heterogeneity across the data (i.e., high variability), moderation analysis indicated that this was not due to treatment type, as they found no significant differences in effect sizes between psychotherapies. What this may suggest is that the TA is a pan-theoretical factor that can consistently show a robust, moderate relationship with patient outcome. This highlights that therapists should perhaps focus on building a strong TA, as it is a central factor in yielding greater patient outcomes across psychotherapies.
Whilst meta-analytic data that measures TA at one particular time point within therapy is important for highlighting its positive relation to therapy outcomes, studies which control for temporal confounds offer more compelling support that a stronger alliance precedes beneficial outcomes (Webb et al., 2012; Zilcha-Mano &amp;amp; Errazuriz, 2015). For instance, Zilcha-Mano and Errazuriz (2015) conducted an RCT with patients allocated to one of several therapist feedback conditions including a condition receiving no feedback. As it would be of ethical concern to allocate patients to a condition whereby the therapist does not attempt to build a TA, the therapist feedback variable offers a similar yet ethical method to conduct such an experiment. Therapist feedback is similar because it enables the dyad to negotiate and collaborate through discussion of the patient’s thoughts, feelings and behaviours, which would build a TA (Zilcha-Mano &amp;amp; Errazuriz, 2015). The researchers assessed TA using the well-established Working Alliance Inventory (WAI; Horvath &amp;amp; Greenberg, 1989), along with patient outcome assessed by overall psychological dysfunction (Lambert et al., 2002). Through controlling for several time points across therapy and previous symptom levels, the RCT found that patients who showed greater TA at a specific time point also showed symptom improvement. This evidence indicates that TA may be causally related to patient outcome as an increase in the TA preceded symptom reduction. Therefore, not only is the TA a pan-theoretical factor that is related to patient outcome, it is perhaps also a way that therapists can deliver a direct improvement in patient outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;developing-a-strong-therapeutic-alliance-early-in-therapy&#34;&gt;Developing a strong therapeutic alliance early in therapy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An additional insight provided from the aforementioned research is that patients who developed a strong TA earlier in the therapy benefited more in outcome (Zilcha-Mano &amp;amp; Errazuriz, 2015). One explanation for these findings may be that the existing traits or predispositions of some patients are more conducive to forming a strong alliance with the therapist (DeRubeis, Brotman &amp;amp; Gibbons, 2005; Zilcha-Mano, 2017). For example, patients in psychotherapy with insecure or avoidant attachment styles may find it difficult to form the deep and satisfactory relationship necessary for a strong TA early in treatment; whereas, those with a secure attachment style are perhaps less likely to find this problematic (Bowlby, 1988). Empirical evidence supports the idea that insecure representations of the self and others predict a weak TA (Smith, Msetfi &amp;amp; Golding, 2010). Importantly, this suggests that therapists should focus their efforts on developing a TA which places more emphasise on the bond alliance if clients struggle to form a strong relationship (Zilcha-Mano, 2017). For instance, therapist delivery methods can draw on practices taken from cognitive analytic therapy (CAT) as this focuses heavily on the TA (Bennett, Parry &amp;amp; Ryle, 2006). Examples of building a bond alliance in practice may include adopting the language of the patient, and more importantly, acknowledging that the patient-therapist relationship contributes to reinforcing or breaking the patient’s negative interpersonal patterns. Although the empirical support for CAT is limited, there is evidence of successful RCTs even amongst those with complex personality disorders that attribute much of their current distress to past relationships (Calvert &amp;amp; Kellett, 2014). Therefore, the way that the therapist builds a bond alliance with the patient during this early therapy period is an important indicator of beneficial patient outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-moderating-effects-of-therapeutic-alliance&#34;&gt;The moderating effects of therapeutic alliance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to TA enhancing patients’ outcome directly, it may also operate by indirectly influencing other non-specific therapy elements. The extent to which the therapist follows the therapy protocol is referred to as treatment adherence, and this may be one mechanism that explains how TA facilitates patients’ outcome (Collyer, Eisler &amp;amp; Woolgar, 2018; Tschuschke et al., 2015). In a naturalistic study consisting of 262 therapy sessions using 8 different psychotherapies, Tschuschke and colleagues (2015) examined the relationship between treatment adherence and other common therapy factors including TA. Ratings for treatment adherence were rigorously assessed by therapists and raters who were blind to the motive of the study. The Helping Alliance Questionnaire (HAQ; Bassler, Potratz &amp;amp; Krauthauser, 1995) was used to assess TA, and the scale items were sufficiently correlated, providing a high internal consistency for the scale. The findings revealed that treatment adherence was significantly predicted by TA and the therapist’s competence. Insight from a recent critical review of the TA in exposure therapy for anxiety-related disorders may provide an explanation for how TA moderates the effect of treatment adherence (Buchholz &amp;amp; Abramowitz, 2020). Exposure therapy requires the patient to gradually confront the feared stimuli over several sessions. A strong TA motivates patients to finish exposure therapy sessions, which leads to a reduction in anxiety-related symptoms. The encouragement and support provided by the therapist may therefore be a necessary component in treatment adherence. Whilst Tschuschke and colleagues did not focus on anxiety-related disorders specifically, TA is seen as a non-specific therapeutic factor that can be of benefit across many, if not all, psychotherapies (Barber, Khalsa &amp;amp; Sharpless, 2010; Webb et al., 2012). Therefore, it is useful for therapists to be aware of the indirect, moderating effects of building a TA. This can help tailor the delivery of psychotherapy to the patient’s needs in order to enhance treatment success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ruptures-and-repairs&#34;&gt;Ruptures and repairs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the ruptures and repairs that occur within therapy are one of the potential underlying mechanisms that improve the TA and patient outcome (Eubanks, Muran &amp;amp; Safran, 2018; Safran, Muran &amp;amp; Eubanks, 2011). A rupture is a breakdown in TA, often due to a challenging emotional bond, a disagreement on the therapy goals, or a dispute over the therapy tasks (Safran &amp;amp; Muran, 2000). Meta-analytic research has indicated that the occurrence of ruptures which are then resolved (i.e., rupture-repair) are moderately associated with positive patient outcome (Safran et al., 2011). Additionally, outcomes can be improved through rupture-repair training (Eubanks et al., 2018). Based on these findings, there are research-supported practices that therapists can deliver to benefit the client. For example, a therapist should be alert to potential ruptures, which may be apparent through patient hostility or dissatisfaction. More so, the therapist should empathise with the client and take responsibility for their contribution to ruptures (Eubanks et al., 2018). These therapeutic practices within the alliance may be inextricably linked to therapist responsiveness (i.e., adapting to the patient’s behaviour; Webb et al., 2010). Thus, ruptures that occur throughout psychotherapy which are dealt with by the therapist’s responsive behaviour will develop the TA, which may provide the necessary understanding and collaboration to reduce the patient’s difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, it is clear that the therapist’s delivery of treatment can benefit from forming a strong TA. Despite other common therapist factors, such as therapist competence, contributing to psychotherapy success, an abundance of meta-analytic research has highlighted the robust association between TA and improved outcomes for patients. What is more, the therapist not only enhances patients’ outcomes through improving the dyadic relationship, but additionally through increasing adherence to treatment. Research which has measured TA and patient outcome across the duration of psychotherapy has indicated that TA may well precede symptom reduction in patients. Additionally, this line of research suggests that those who form a strong TA early in therapy benefit more in outcome.  Nevertheless, an important aspect of establishing a strong TA is based on the therapist’s responsiveness to ruptures that will inevitably arise throughout psychotherapy. Taken together, the aforementioned research suggests that patients’ difficulties can be reduced by the therapist delivering psychotherapy in a manner that is conducive to improving the TA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To what extent should Alzheimer’s Disease be considered a unitary disorder?</title>
      <link>/essay/ad-essay/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/essay/ad-essay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disorder with biomarkers that can be assessed based on clinical function, brain structure, neuropathology, and genetics (Trojanowski et al., 2010; Webster, Bachstetter, Nelson, Schmitt &amp;amp; Eldik, 2014). Clinically, memory impairment, especially episodic memory, is often the earliest and most prominent symptom in AD (McKhann et al., 2011). This clinical presentation is in line with the proposed neuropathological changes which, according to the Braak stages, begins with atrophy from neurofibrillary tangles (NFT) in the transentorhinal cortex and progressively spreads throughout the medial temporal lobes (MTL) and into neocortical regions (Braak &amp;amp; Braak, 1991). As many AD patients adhere to this clinical and neuropathological progression, it could be stated that AD is a unitary disorder. However, despite this typical pattern, there are a significant amount of AD patients who present atypical and non-amnesic subtypes which do not conform to the Braak stages (Galton, Patterson, Xuereb &amp;amp; Hodges, 2000; Murray et al., 2011; Peter et al., 2014). Therefore, the following essay will argue that AD should not be considered as a unitary disorder because of the high heterogeneity in clinical, neuroimaging, and neuropathological presentations. Firstly, post-mortem research will show that neuropathological change can progress in regions outside of the MTL. Secondly, data-driven analysis will reveal amnesic and non-amnesic AD clinical clusters. Thirdly, converging findings from clinical and neuroimaging research will shed light on AD variation. Finally, the distinct features of early-onset AD and late-onset AD will suggest that a unitary view of AD is incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;neuropathological-evidence&#34;&gt;Neuropathological evidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seminal post-mortem research as well as meta-analytic data indicate that the neuropathology distribution may not necessarily follow the typical AD progression as proposed by the Braak stages (Ferreira, Nordberg &amp;amp; Westman, 2020; Murray et al., 2011). In 889 post-mortem AD cases, Murray and colleagues (2011) measured the density of NFTs and senile plaques in each brain to determine underlying AD pathology. Post-mortem analysis ascertains that all cases were of AD because pathology can be analysed at the cellular level. A quantitative algorithm classified each case into three distinct subtypes: typical, hippocampal-spared, and limbic-predominant. The latter two subtypes are atypical neuropathology distributions and accounted for 25% of all cases. The typical cases had a higher count of NFTs in the transentorhinal cortex and MTL, which follows the Braak stages. In contrast, the hippocampal-spared and limbic-predominant subtypes showed increased NFT density in neocortical regions and in limbic regions including the amygdala, respectively. This suggests that AD does not necessarily present with atrophy in the MTL as a noteworthy proportion of confirmed cases show preservation in these areas and NFT burden outside of the MTL. Thus, AD pathology does not always adhere to a single distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clinical-presentations-of-ad&#34;&gt;Clinical presentations of AD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following from this, the neuropathology distribution is thought to govern the AD clinical symptoms (Galton et al., 2000). Therefore, clinical symptom variability should also be apparent. A systematic review of 8 studies with over 4000 probable AD subjects shows differential clinical presentations using cluster analysis (Martorelli, Sudo &amp;amp; Charchat-Fichman, 2019). Cluster analysis provides an unbiased, data-driven approach to identify distinct cognitive patterns within neuropsychological data which is often assessed with the Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE). The MMSE is an extensively used neuropsychological test for assessing global cognitive impairment with domains including attention, orientation, memory, language and visuospatial skills (Folstein, Folstein &amp;amp; McHugh, 1975). The general review findings show that AD patients not only cluster into the typical memory impairment subtypes, but a significant amount also cluster into groups with relatively spared memory or present more global cognitive deficits which is not explained by disease severity (e.g., Davidson et al., 2010; Stopford, Snowden, Thompson &amp;amp; Neary, 2008). These results refute the unitary view that AD cases only present with focal memory impairments.
To elaborate on these findings, one strong methodological study within the review used latent class analysis with data from 938 probable AD patients (Scheltens et al., 2016). A battery of neuropsychological tests was analysed and the MMSE was used as a covariate to account for clustering of cognitive impairment severity. This provides more confidence that differences within and between the cognitive domains were revealed rather than being attributed to disease progression. Three main subtypes were identified: 2 memory-impaired clusters (i.e., mild or moderate amnesic AD patients), 3 memory-spared clusters (i.e., deficits in language and visuospatial ability, deficits in executive function, and deficits exclusively in visuospatial ability) and 3 memory-indifferent clusters (i.e., variants of global cognitive deficits). Whilst the memory-impaired clusters included the most patients (43%), the atypical clusters (i.e., memory-spared and memory-indifferent) accounted for the majority of patients’ clinical presentations when combined (57%). Therefore, AD does not necessarily present with focal memory deficits, which is supported in additional cluster analyses (Peter et al., 2014; Ralph, Patterson, Graham, Dawson &amp;amp; Hodges, 2003; Qiu, Jacobs, Messer, Salmon &amp;amp; Feldman, 2019). Taken together, data-driven research supports heterogeneity in AD symptoms to reveal a multifaceted disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;neuroimaging-evidence&#34;&gt;Neuroimaging evidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging evidence that maps brain atrophy onto clinical symptoms offers converging support that the AD subtypes are truly heterogeneous (Kate et al., 2018; Taler &amp;amp; Phillips, 2008). Across three independent datasets with 707 prodromal AD and AD cases, a data-driven cluster analysis classified brain atrophy using structural MRI and clinical symptoms into subgroups (Kate et al., 2018). Both prodromal AD and AD cases had underlying amyloid pathology (i.e., an AD biomarker; Dubois et al., 2014), with the former having a clinical diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment. The statistical analysis revealed four subtypes with distinct brain atrophy and clinical presentations. Those with medial-temporal atrophy had the lowest memory and language scores. Cases of parieto-occipital atrophy had poor visuospatial and executive scores. In addition, the mild atrophy subgroup had the highest global cognition scores, and the diffuse atrophy subgroup displayed atrophy in the frontal and temporal lobes and presented low memory scores yet average cognitive scores in other domains. Firstly, these results show that underlying brain atrophy maps onto distinct clinical symptoms which provides more support for genuine variation in AD. Secondly, these subtypes can even be distinguished in prodromal AD, despite the neurodegeneration being in the earliest stage when it is less apparent. Thus, brain atrophy is consistent with clinical symptoms in indicating a disease that has multiple degeneration pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clinical-presentations-do-not-always-match-the-brain-atrophy&#34;&gt;Clinical presentations do not always match the brain atrophy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is noteworthy to state that the cognitive domain that is intended to be clinically assessed does not always correspond to the expected brain atrophy (Stopford, Thompson, Neary, Richardson &amp;amp; Snowden, 2012; Joubert et al., 2016). This limitation of clinical assessment is clear in Stopford and colleagues’ (2012) work, in which they assessed AD patients along with fronto-temporal dementia (FTD) patients who have prominent frontal lobe dysfunction. AD patients can show similar clinical deficits to those with FTD, displaying poor performance on working memory and executive tasks such as planning, inhibition, and attention (Lafleche &amp;amp; Albert, 1995; Perry, Watson &amp;amp; Hodges, 2000). As these tasks are associated with frontal lobe functions, this reinforces the idea that AD patients can suffer from frontal lobe pathology. However, AD patients do not often show the personality and behavioural impairments which are characteristic symptoms of FTD and therefore of frontal dysfunction. More so, comparison of executive task performance between AD and FTD has highlighted, upon close examination, that whilst FTD patients show problems with attention and response inhibition, AD patients seem to perform poorly on these tasks because of poor short-term memory load. Short-term memory capacity is functionally localised to temporo-parietal regions, which suggests that this may be the primary deficit in executive tasks, rather than a frontal deficit (Stopford et al., 2012). A low sensitivity in neuropsychological testing may therefore lead to incorrect claims of the brain atrophy. Whilst this is an important shortcoming of some neuropsychological testing, the aforementioned research shows that an extensive neuropsychology test battery along with neuroimaging and neuropathology evidence strongly suggests against a single presentation of AD (e.g., Kate et al., 2018; Martorelli et al., 2019; Murray et al., 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-can-early-onset-alzheimers-disease-tell-us&#34;&gt;What can early-onset Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, early-onset AD (EOAD; &amp;lt;65 years old) and late-onset AD (LOAD; &amp;gt;65 years old) reveal important clinical variability that would be overlooked if AD was considered a unitary disorder. EOAD is usually characterised by non-amnesic deficits as well as presenting with atrophy outside of the hippocampus and MTL (Koedam et al., 2010; Poulakis et al., 2018; Stopford et al., 2012). In contrast to this, LOAD follows a more typical AD presentation with memory impairment being the primary deficit, along with temporal lobe atrophy (Frisoni et al., 2007). In support of this difference, Joubert and colleagues (2016) assessed 40 EOAD and LOAD patients, who provided biomarker evidence of amyloid pathology, on an extensive battery of neuropsychological testing. AD patients were age- and education-matched to healthy controls. The relevant findings revealed that EOAD patients performed more poorly than LOAD patients on executive and visuoconstructional tasks. LOAD patients were significantly more impaired in semantic memory, with 100% of cases reaching the threshold for clinical impairment (i.e., -1.96 SD) compared to only 50% of EOAD cases. More so, LOAD patients had a marginally significant greater impairment in episodic memory tasks. Caution should be taken when interpreting non-significant findings (Makin &amp;amp; Tamar, 2019), but there is reason to believe that LOAD patients are more impaired than EOAD patients in episodic memory. Firstly, a strict correction method was used which may have resulted in a type 2 error. Secondly, as mentioned, EOAD is usually characterised by non-amnesic deficits so a greater memory performance would be expected when compared to LOAD. These characteristic features between age groups suggest that LOAD may be similar to typical AD. However, EOAD presents with contrasting deficits which cannot be explained by a unitary view of AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the clinical, neuroimaging, and neuropathology evidence discussed indicates that AD may well have multiple subtypes rather than reflecting a single disorder. Post-mortem research has shown that the distribution of neuropathology in AD does not necessarily follow the Braak stages. Systematic research of cluster analyses has revealed that whilst memory impairment is a prominent subtype of AD, there are important subtypes with focal non-amnesic deficits. More so, converging evidence from neuroimaging and neuropsychological testing supports the notion that AD, and even prodromal AD, present with multiple subtypes. Finally, the distinct features of EOAD and LOAD indicates that a unitary view of AD is insufficient at explaining this variation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
