<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matthew Waddington</title>
    <link>/author/matthew-waddington/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/matthew-waddington/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Matthew Waddington</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/author/matthew-waddington/avatar_hu73d6ed0502846ebd736033e6a19be3d7_374631_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Matthew Waddington</title>
      <link>/author/matthew-waddington/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Young, formidable men show greater sensitivity to facial cues of dominance</title>
      <link>/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of dementia</title>
      <link>/blogpost/dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blogpost/dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What’s one of the main worries people have about getting old? Is it the idea of going to your grandson’s 18th birthday party and forgetting his age as soon as you arrive? How about developing an uncontrollable tremor? Could it also be the spontaneous change in your personality and behaviour?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these examples come under the umbrella term, dementia, but each are different diseases. It’s no wonder this is a big worry for many, there are 50 million cases of dementia worldwide and this number is only rising [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might well then ask, what can be done to prevent this terrible disease? Before we answer this, let&amp;rsquo;s introduce a couple of case examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane, a 59-year-old secondary school English teacher, has been looking forward to a peaceful retirement after decades of being surrounded by hyperactive teenagers. As of recently, however, she’s taken time off work after struggling to navigate herself around the school, remember the students’ names, and recall key novels she taught. After a consultation with her GP and several tests, Jane was diagnosed with early-onset Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, a 72-year-old man named Andrew has just divorced his wife after suddenly becoming hostile and showing unusual acts of impulsion. For instance, last month, Andrew and his wife were eating at an Italian restaurant and moments later both of them were drenched in red wine. Andrew spontaneously poured Merlot all over his wife. With his wife left worried and perplexed after these recurring events, she decided to get a doctor involved. Andrew went through a series of brain scans and psychological testing and the doctor diagnosed him with fronto-temporal dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two cases of dementia, two completely different experiences. The first case relates to classical memory problems whereby knowledge of events and facts become more difficult to remember. Whereas, Andrew’s case is to do with unusual acts of behaviour and personality changes. These are two of the many faces of dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientifically speaking, each of these faces are one of several neurodegenerative diseases. For anyone interested in the brain areas involved in the two cases we described, Jane was likely to have problems in the hippocampal and medial temporal lobe areas [2]. On the other hand, Andrew was likely to have issues in the frontal lobe region of the brain [3]. So it’s not just the symptoms that differ, but the brain areas that are affected too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even then, each face of dementia has its own complications. The case from Jane may be typical of Alzheimer’s disease, but the symptoms do not always involve memory loss. A scientific study with nearly 1000 patients found that 57% of those with Alzheimer’s disease did not show memory loss symptoms [4]. Instead, they showed difficulty with language, executing actions, and visual ability. If not classical memory problems, what is it then that determines whether someone has Alzheimer’s disease or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, one of the major difficulties in this kind of science is finding the balance between reaching a diagnosis and picking up on the nuance within each type of dementia. Right now, the only way to truly know what type of dementia someone has is to examine the brain tissue after death. Hardly useful for making a plan of action!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re still reading this, it may be because you know someone personally with dementia (or you’re all just a curious bunch!). Has a doctor ever refused to give that person a diagnosis of a certain type of dementia? Or even given a general diagnosis of dementia?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads us to another really important point. That is, those with suspected dementia need to be able to complete the testing in order to get a diagnosis. Otherwise, they’re likely left with a general label of cognitive impairment. The unfortunate truth is that a diagnosis is unlikely to be useful and accurate when the testing cannot be completed, and it’s often a sign that the disease has progressed too far to act upon it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that being said, all hope is not lost. For some types of dementia, such as Parkinson’s disease, there are effective medications that can help with the symptoms. A couple of the main symptoms of Parkinson’s disease include a lack of movement control and stiffness in bodily limbs. For some patients, the prescribed medicine can really help take these symptoms away [5]. And it’s not just medication. Fascinatingly, there is even research to show that music and dance can help manage these symptoms and improve quality of life [6]. Time to get your gran to do the cha-cha slide!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to get back to the first question, how do we prevent dementia? The truth is, there won’t be a cure for dementia. There is no one-size-fits-all approach. Rather, scientists are working on treatments to slow and maybe even prevent each type of dementia. Research in areas such as early detection of dementia and drug treatment is promising [7]. This gives those suffering an opportunity to act upon early warning signs and then they may well remember their grandson’s 18th birthday party. Now, that would be something to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;World Health Organisation (2020, September 21). Dementia: Rates of dementia. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/dementia&#34;&gt;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/dementia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Murray, M. E., Graff-Radford, N. R., Ross, O. A., Petersen, R. C., Duara, R., &amp;amp; Dickson, D. W. (2011). Neuropathologically defined subtypes of Alzheimer’s disease with distinct clinical   &lt;br&gt;
characteristics: A retrospective study. Lancet Neurology, 10(9), 785–796. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70156-9&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70156-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stopford, C. L., Thompson, J. C., Neary, D., Richardson, A. M. T., &amp;amp; Snowden, J. S. (2012). Working memory, attention, and executive function in Alzheimer’s disease and frontotemporal&lt;br&gt;
dementia. Cortex, 48(4), 429–446. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2010.12.002&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2010.12.002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheltens, N. M. E., Galindo-Garre, F., Pijnenburg, Y. A. L., van der Vlies, A. E., Smits, L. L., Koene, T., Teunissen, C. E., Barkhof, F., Wattjes, M. P., Scheltens, P., &amp;amp; van der Flier, W.     M. (2016). The identification of cognitive subtypes in Alzheimer’s disease dementia using latent class analysis. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp;amp; Psychiatry, 87(3), 235–243.   &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1136/jnnp-2014-309582&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1136/jnnp-2014-309582&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schapira, A. H. V. (2007). Treatment Options in the Modern Management of Parkinson Disease. Archives of Neurology, 64(8), 1083. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1001/archneur.64.8.1083&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1001/archneur.64.8.1083&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bek, J., Arakaki, A. I., Lawrence, A., Sullivan, M., Ganapathy, G., &amp;amp; Poliakoff, E. (2020). Dance and Parkinson’s: A review and exploration of the role of cognitive representations of action.    Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, 109, 16–28. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.12.023&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.12.023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ahmed, M. R., Zhang, Y., Feng, Z., Lo, B., Inan, O. T., &amp;amp; Liao, H. (2019). Neuroimaging and Machine Learning for Dementia Diagnosis: Recent Advancements and Future Prospects. IEEE Reviews in     Biomedical Engineering, 12, 19–33. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2018.2886237&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2018.2886237&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To what extent should Alzheimer’s Disease be considered a unitary disorder?</title>
      <link>/essay/ad-essay/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/essay/ad-essay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disorder with biomarkers that can be assessed based on clinical function, brain structure, neuropathology, and genetics (Trojanowski et al., 2010; Webster, Bachstetter, Nelson, Schmitt &amp;amp; Eldik, 2014). Clinically, memory impairment, especially episodic memory, is often the earliest and most prominent symptom in AD (McKhann et al., 2011). This clinical presentation is in line with the proposed neuropathological changes which, according to the Braak stages, begins with atrophy from neurofibrillary tangles (NFT) in the transentorhinal cortex and progressively spreads throughout the medial temporal lobes (MTL) and into neocortical regions (Braak &amp;amp; Braak, 1991). As many AD patients adhere to this clinical and neuropathological progression, it could be stated that AD is a unitary disorder. However, despite this typical pattern, there are a significant amount of AD patients who present atypical and non-amnesic subtypes which do not conform to the Braak stages (Galton, Patterson, Xuereb &amp;amp; Hodges, 2000; Murray et al., 2011; Peter et al., 2014). Therefore, the following essay will argue that AD should not be considered as a unitary disorder because of the high heterogeneity in clinical, neuroimaging, and neuropathological presentations. Firstly, post-mortem research will show that neuropathological change can progress in regions outside of the MTL. Secondly, data-driven analysis will reveal amnesic and non-amnesic AD clinical clusters. Thirdly, converging findings from clinical and neuroimaging research will shed light on AD variation. Finally, the distinct features of early-onset AD and late-onset AD will suggest that a unitary view of AD is incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;neuropathological-evidence&#34;&gt;Neuropathological evidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seminal post-mortem research as well as meta-analytic data indicate that the neuropathology distribution may not necessarily follow the typical AD progression as proposed by the Braak stages (Ferreira, Nordberg &amp;amp; Westman, 2020; Murray et al., 2011). In 889 post-mortem AD cases, Murray and colleagues (2011) measured the density of NFTs and senile plaques in each brain to determine underlying AD pathology. Post-mortem analysis ascertains that all cases were of AD because pathology can be analysed at the cellular level. A quantitative algorithm classified each case into three distinct subtypes: typical, hippocampal-spared, and limbic-predominant. The latter two subtypes are atypical neuropathology distributions and accounted for 25% of all cases. The typical cases had a higher count of NFTs in the transentorhinal cortex and MTL, which follows the Braak stages. In contrast, the hippocampal-spared and limbic-predominant subtypes showed increased NFT density in neocortical regions and in limbic regions including the amygdala, respectively. This suggests that AD does not necessarily present with atrophy in the MTL as a noteworthy proportion of confirmed cases show preservation in these areas and NFT burden outside of the MTL. Thus, AD pathology does not always adhere to a single distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clinical-presentations-of-ad&#34;&gt;Clinical presentations of AD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following from this, the neuropathology distribution is thought to govern the AD clinical symptoms (Galton et al., 2000). Therefore, clinical symptom variability should also be apparent. A systematic review of 8 studies with over 4000 probable AD subjects shows differential clinical presentations using cluster analysis (Martorelli, Sudo &amp;amp; Charchat-Fichman, 2019). Cluster analysis provides an unbiased, data-driven approach to identify distinct cognitive patterns within neuropsychological data which is often assessed with the Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE). The MMSE is an extensively used neuropsychological test for assessing global cognitive impairment with domains including attention, orientation, memory, language and visuospatial skills (Folstein, Folstein &amp;amp; McHugh, 1975). The general review findings show that AD patients not only cluster into the typical memory impairment subtypes, but a significant amount also cluster into groups with relatively spared memory or present more global cognitive deficits which is not explained by disease severity (e.g., Davidson et al., 2010; Stopford, Snowden, Thompson &amp;amp; Neary, 2008). These results refute the unitary view that AD cases only present with focal memory impairments.
To elaborate on these findings, one strong methodological study within the review used latent class analysis with data from 938 probable AD patients (Scheltens et al., 2016). A battery of neuropsychological tests was analysed and the MMSE was used as a covariate to account for clustering of cognitive impairment severity. This provides more confidence that differences within and between the cognitive domains were revealed rather than being attributed to disease progression. Three main subtypes were identified: 2 memory-impaired clusters (i.e., mild or moderate amnesic AD patients), 3 memory-spared clusters (i.e., deficits in language and visuospatial ability, deficits in executive function, and deficits exclusively in visuospatial ability) and 3 memory-indifferent clusters (i.e., variants of global cognitive deficits). Whilst the memory-impaired clusters included the most patients (43%), the atypical clusters (i.e., memory-spared and memory-indifferent) accounted for the majority of patients’ clinical presentations when combined (57%). Therefore, AD does not necessarily present with focal memory deficits, which is supported in additional cluster analyses (Peter et al., 2014; Ralph, Patterson, Graham, Dawson &amp;amp; Hodges, 2003; Qiu, Jacobs, Messer, Salmon &amp;amp; Feldman, 2019). Taken together, data-driven research supports heterogeneity in AD symptoms to reveal a multifaceted disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;neuroimaging-evidence&#34;&gt;Neuroimaging evidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging evidence that maps brain atrophy onto clinical symptoms offers converging support that the AD subtypes are truly heterogeneous (Kate et al., 2018; Taler &amp;amp; Phillips, 2008). Across three independent datasets with 707 prodromal AD and AD cases, a data-driven cluster analysis classified brain atrophy using structural MRI and clinical symptoms into subgroups (Kate et al., 2018). Both prodromal AD and AD cases had underlying amyloid pathology (i.e., an AD biomarker; Dubois et al., 2014), with the former having a clinical diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment. The statistical analysis revealed four subtypes with distinct brain atrophy and clinical presentations. Those with medial-temporal atrophy had the lowest memory and language scores. Cases of parieto-occipital atrophy had poor visuospatial and executive scores. In addition, the mild atrophy subgroup had the highest global cognition scores, and the diffuse atrophy subgroup displayed atrophy in the frontal and temporal lobes and presented low memory scores yet average cognitive scores in other domains. Firstly, these results show that underlying brain atrophy maps onto distinct clinical symptoms which provides more support for genuine variation in AD. Secondly, these subtypes can even be distinguished in prodromal AD, despite the neurodegeneration being in the earliest stage when it is less apparent. Thus, brain atrophy is consistent with clinical symptoms in indicating a disease that has multiple degeneration pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clinical-presentations-do-not-always-match-the-brain-atrophy&#34;&gt;Clinical presentations do not always match the brain atrophy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is noteworthy to state that the cognitive domain that is intended to be clinically assessed does not always correspond to the expected brain atrophy (Stopford, Thompson, Neary, Richardson &amp;amp; Snowden, 2012; Joubert et al., 2016). This limitation of clinical assessment is clear in Stopford and colleagues’ (2012) work, in which they assessed AD patients along with fronto-temporal dementia (FTD) patients who have prominent frontal lobe dysfunction. AD patients can show similar clinical deficits to those with FTD, displaying poor performance on working memory and executive tasks such as planning, inhibition, and attention (Lafleche &amp;amp; Albert, 1995; Perry, Watson &amp;amp; Hodges, 2000). As these tasks are associated with frontal lobe functions, this reinforces the idea that AD patients can suffer from frontal lobe pathology. However, AD patients do not often show the personality and behavioural impairments which are characteristic symptoms of FTD and therefore of frontal dysfunction. More so, comparison of executive task performance between AD and FTD has highlighted, upon close examination, that whilst FTD patients show problems with attention and response inhibition, AD patients seem to perform poorly on these tasks because of poor short-term memory load. Short-term memory capacity is functionally localised to temporo-parietal regions, which suggests that this may be the primary deficit in executive tasks, rather than a frontal deficit (Stopford et al., 2012). A low sensitivity in neuropsychological testing may therefore lead to incorrect claims of the brain atrophy. Whilst this is an important shortcoming of some neuropsychological testing, the aforementioned research shows that an extensive neuropsychology test battery along with neuroimaging and neuropathology evidence strongly suggests against a single presentation of AD (e.g., Kate et al., 2018; Martorelli et al., 2019; Murray et al., 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-can-early-onset-alzheimers-disease-tell-us&#34;&gt;What can early-onset Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, early-onset AD (EOAD; &amp;lt;65 years old) and late-onset AD (LOAD; &amp;gt;65 years old) reveal important clinical variability that would be overlooked if AD was considered a unitary disorder. EOAD is usually characterised by non-amnesic deficits as well as presenting with atrophy outside of the hippocampus and MTL (Koedam et al., 2010; Poulakis et al., 2018; Stopford et al., 2012). In contrast to this, LOAD follows a more typical AD presentation with memory impairment being the primary deficit, along with temporal lobe atrophy (Frisoni et al., 2007). In support of this difference, Joubert and colleagues (2016) assessed 40 EOAD and LOAD patients, who provided biomarker evidence of amyloid pathology, on an extensive battery of neuropsychological testing. AD patients were age- and education-matched to healthy controls. The relevant findings revealed that EOAD patients performed more poorly than LOAD patients on executive and visuoconstructional tasks. LOAD patients were significantly more impaired in semantic memory, with 100% of cases reaching the threshold for clinical impairment (i.e., -1.96 SD) compared to only 50% of EOAD cases. More so, LOAD patients had a marginally significant greater impairment in episodic memory tasks. Caution should be taken when interpreting non-significant findings (Makin &amp;amp; Tamar, 2019), but there is reason to believe that LOAD patients are more impaired than EOAD patients in episodic memory. Firstly, a strict correction method was used which may have resulted in a type 2 error. Secondly, as mentioned, EOAD is usually characterised by non-amnesic deficits so a greater memory performance would be expected when compared to LOAD. These characteristic features between age groups suggest that LOAD may be similar to typical AD. However, EOAD presents with contrasting deficits which cannot be explained by a unitary view of AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the clinical, neuroimaging, and neuropathology evidence discussed indicates that AD may well have multiple subtypes rather than reflecting a single disorder. Post-mortem research has shown that the distribution of neuropathology in AD does not necessarily follow the Braak stages. Systematic research of cluster analyses has revealed that whilst memory impairment is a prominent subtype of AD, there are important subtypes with focal non-amnesic deficits. More so, converging evidence from neuroimaging and neuropsychological testing supports the notion that AD, and even prodromal AD, present with multiple subtypes. Finally, the distinct features of EOAD and LOAD indicates that a unitary view of AD is insufficient at explaining this variation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
