<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog Posts | Matthew Waddington</title>
    <link>/blogpost/</link>
      <atom:link href="/blogpost/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Blog Posts</title>
      <link>/blogpost/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of dementia</title>
      <link>/blogpost/dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blogpost/dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What’s one of the main worries people have about getting old? Is it the idea of going to your grandson’s 18th birthday party and forgetting his age as soon as you arrive? How about developing an uncontrollable tremor? Could it also be the spontaneous change in your personality and behaviour?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these examples come under the umbrella term, dementia, but each are different diseases. It’s no wonder this is a big worry for many, there are 50 million cases of dementia worldwide and this number is only rising [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might well then ask, what can be done to prevent this terrible disease? Before we answer this, let&amp;rsquo;s introduce a couple of case examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane, a 59-year-old secondary school English teacher, has been looking forward to a peaceful retirement after decades of being surrounded by hyperactive teenagers. As of recently, however, she’s taken time off work after struggling to navigate herself around the school, remember the students’ names, and recall key novels she taught. After a consultation with her GP and several tests, Jane was diagnosed with early-onset Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, a 72-year-old man named Andrew has just divorced his wife after suddenly becoming hostile and showing unusual acts of impulsion. For instance, last month, Andrew and his wife were eating at an Italian restaurant and moments later both of them were drenched in red wine. Andrew spontaneously poured Merlot all over his wife. With his wife left worried and perplexed after these recurring events, she decided to get a doctor involved. Andrew went through a series of brain scans and psychological testing and the doctor diagnosed him with fronto-temporal dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two cases of dementia, two completely different experiences. The first case relates to classical memory problems whereby knowledge of events and facts become more difficult to remember. Whereas, Andrew’s case is to do with unusual acts of behaviour and personality changes. These are two of the many faces of dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientifically speaking, each of these faces are one of several neurodegenerative diseases. For anyone interested in the brain areas involved in the two cases we described, Jane was likely to have problems in the hippocampal and medial temporal lobe areas [2]. On the other hand, Andrew was likely to have issues in the frontal lobe region of the brain [3]. So it’s not just the symptoms that differ, but the brain areas that are affected too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even then, each face of dementia has its own complications. The case from Jane may be typical of Alzheimer’s disease, but the symptoms do not always involve memory loss. A scientific study with nearly 1000 patients found that 57% of those with Alzheimer’s disease did not show memory loss symptoms [4]. Instead, they showed difficulty with language, executing actions, and visual ability. If not classical memory problems, what is it then that determines whether someone has Alzheimer’s disease or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, one of the major difficulties in this kind of science is finding the balance between reaching a diagnosis and picking up on the nuance within each type of dementia. Right now, the only way to truly know what type of dementia someone has is to examine the brain tissue after death. Hardly useful for making a plan of action!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re still reading this, it may be because you know someone personally with dementia (or you’re all just a curious bunch!). Has a doctor ever refused to give that person a diagnosis of a certain type of dementia? Or even given a general diagnosis of dementia?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads us to another really important point. That is, those with suspected dementia need to be able to complete the testing in order to get a diagnosis. Otherwise, they’re likely left with a general label of cognitive impairment. The unfortunate truth is that a diagnosis is unlikely to be useful and accurate when the testing cannot be completed, and it’s often a sign that the disease has progressed too far to act upon it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that being said, all hope is not lost. For some types of dementia, such as Parkinson’s disease, there are effective medications that can help with the symptoms. A couple of the main symptoms of Parkinson’s disease include a lack of movement control and stiffness in bodily limbs. For some patients, the prescribed medicine can really help take these symptoms away [5]. And it’s not just medication. Fascinatingly, there is even research to show that music and dance can help manage these symptoms and improve quality of life [6]. Time to get your gran to do the cha-cha slide!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to get back to the first question, how do we prevent dementia? The truth is, there won’t be a cure for dementia. There is no one-size-fits-all approach. Rather, scientists are working on treatments to slow and maybe even prevent each type of dementia. Research in areas such as early detection of dementia and drug treatment is promising [7]. This gives those suffering an opportunity to act upon early warning signs and then they may well remember their grandson’s 18th birthday party. Now, that would be something to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;World Health Organisation (2020, September 21). Dementia: Rates of dementia. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/dementia&#34;&gt;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/dementia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Murray, M. E., Graff-Radford, N. R., Ross, O. A., Petersen, R. C., Duara, R., &amp;amp; Dickson, D. W. (2011). Neuropathologically defined subtypes of Alzheimer’s disease with distinct clinical   &lt;br&gt;
characteristics: A retrospective study. Lancet Neurology, 10(9), 785–796. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70156-9&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70156-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stopford, C. L., Thompson, J. C., Neary, D., Richardson, A. M. T., &amp;amp; Snowden, J. S. (2012). Working memory, attention, and executive function in Alzheimer’s disease and frontotemporal&lt;br&gt;
dementia. Cortex, 48(4), 429–446. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2010.12.002&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2010.12.002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheltens, N. M. E., Galindo-Garre, F., Pijnenburg, Y. A. L., van der Vlies, A. E., Smits, L. L., Koene, T., Teunissen, C. E., Barkhof, F., Wattjes, M. P., Scheltens, P., &amp;amp; van der Flier, W.     M. (2016). The identification of cognitive subtypes in Alzheimer’s disease dementia using latent class analysis. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp;amp; Psychiatry, 87(3), 235–243.   &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1136/jnnp-2014-309582&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1136/jnnp-2014-309582&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schapira, A. H. V. (2007). Treatment Options in the Modern Management of Parkinson Disease. Archives of Neurology, 64(8), 1083. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1001/archneur.64.8.1083&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1001/archneur.64.8.1083&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bek, J., Arakaki, A. I., Lawrence, A., Sullivan, M., Ganapathy, G., &amp;amp; Poliakoff, E. (2020). Dance and Parkinson’s: A review and exploration of the role of cognitive representations of action.    Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, 109, 16–28. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.12.023&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.12.023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ahmed, M. R., Zhang, Y., Feng, Z., Lo, B., Inan, O. T., &amp;amp; Liao, H. (2019). Neuroimaging and Machine Learning for Dementia Diagnosis: Recent Advancements and Future Prospects. IEEE Reviews in     Biomedical Engineering, 12, 19–33. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2018.2886237&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2018.2886237&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
